James Luther Adams Papers
James Luther Adams Papers
ca. 1921-1990
Adams, James Luther, 1901-1994.
81.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American theologian, Unitarian Universalist, Professor of Religion. Predominately correspondence, the remainder of the collection consists of financial records, photographs, printed material, and writings including examinations, notes, and a typescript of the translation of Ernst Troeltsch's Historism and Its Problems, First Book: The Logical Problem of the Philosophy of History (Tübingen, Germany, 1925).
146330
Biographical History
James Luther Adams (1901-1994) was a Unitarian parish minister, social activist, journal editor, distinguished scholar, translator and editor of major German theologians, prolific author, and highly respected divinity school professor for more than forty years.
Born to fundamentalist Christian parents in eastern Washington state, during his college years he turned to Unitarianism; after graduation from the University of Minnesota he went to Harvard Divinity School and began his search for "a faith which could be held intellectually accountable." He served as pastor for two Massachusetts Unitarian churches while earning a Master's degree in comparative literature from Harvard and teaching English at Boston University. A strike at the Pequot Mills in Salem during his pastorate led him to address local labor issues from the pulpit, demonstrating his growing belief that "a liberal church can and should make itself a faithful voice for the voiceless oppressed."
In 1935 Adams joined the faculty of Unitarian and Universalist Meadville/Lombard Theological School in Chicago, where he was to remain until 1943. Before beginning his work there he requested and received a one-year leave to study in Europe, where he became involved with the underground church movement opposing the Nazi regime. His experience there confirmed his feeling that the church could and should be directly outspoken against evil rather than relying on vague sermons about love and tolerance.
Adams' teaching was not limited to Meadville/Lombard, nor did he cease his own learning. He was on the faculty of the Federated Theological Faculties of the University of Chicago from 1943 to 1956 and in 1945 earned a Ph.D. from the University of Chicago. He became involved with local politics, an advocate of open and honest government, and a friend of liberal politicians Paul Douglas and Adlai Stevenson. In 1957 Adams returned to Harvard Divinity School as a professor, where he stayed until 1968; he continued to teach at Andover Newton Theological Seminary and Meadville/Lombard.
Adams' writings focused largely on the theology of social ethics and addressed a comprehensive range of topics, from politics to the arts and from angels to AIDS. He also wrote extensively on the history and theory of voluntary associations in a democratic culture. Adams was also interested in liberal German theologians, and among his other writings he found time to translate, edit and interpret the works of Paul Tillich, Ernst Troeltsch, and Karl Holl.
Adams' fascination with the history and origin of ideas led Edwin Wilson, leader of the Unitarian humanists, to remark, "James Luther Adams believes in salvation by bibliography." Adams's reply was, "There is no such thing as the immaculate conception of an idea." Although his impatience with abstraction and his criticism of liberal religion rankled some of his more established colleagues, he was deeply respected by a great many Unitarians as a constructive reformer, worth listening to for the depth and breadth of his concerns.
[Adapted from the article "James Luther Adams," in the Dictionary of Unitarian and Universalist Biography.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The James Luther Adams Papers consist of the initial large collection and three later accessions which have not been integrated.
Original accession
The original collection is predominantly incoming Correspondence. This has been arranged alphabetically by correspondent, institution, organization, or, in rare instances, subject. The latter folders will often contain correspondence and notes from several individuals, as well as Adams' own outgoing carbons. Dates of the correspondence span much of Adams' career and the Twentieth Century, covering professional topics as well as speaking engagements, writings, student recommendations, activities, and comments from the public sector on his speeches and writings. Following the alphabetical sequence are single folders containing the following: unidentified correspondence and fragments, and family correspondence.
The collection also includes a small amount of Financial material and Miscellany, the latter including photographs and printed material. Writings contains samples of examinations, notes, and the xeroxed typescript of a translation of Ernst Troeltsh's Historism and its problems, First book: The logical problem of the philosophy of history. Drs. Adams and D.B.Robertson (donor of the typescript) were members of the translation committee.
1992 accession
The 1992 accession consists entirely of Correspondence-subject files, arranged alphabetically.
1993 accession
The 1993 accession consists of Correspondence-subject files and Writings, the latter including articles, essays, interviews, lectures, and other types.
1995 accession
The 1995 accession consists of Correspondence-subject files and Writings, the latter including autobiographical writings, articles, lectures, and sermons. This accession also contains a small amount of Memorabilia, including 26 audiocassettes, many labeled "Autobiography."
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence and correspondence-subject files are arranged alphabetically. Writings for the original and 1995 accessions are arranged alphabetically by type and then by title; writings for the 1993 accession are not subdivided by type but are arranged alphabetically by title.
Note that each accession begins again with Box 1. When requesting boxes, be sure to indicate which accession is desired.
Subject and Genre Headings
Religion and Philosophy; Church and clergy; Activism and social reform; Adams, James Luther, 1901-1994; Troeltsch, Ernst, 1865-1923 -- Historismus und seine Probleme. Band 1. English.; Educators -- United States.; Religion and ethics.; Religion and state -- United States.; Theologians -- United States.; Theology.; Theology -- Study and teaching.; Unitarian Universalists -- United States.; Audiocassettes.; Correspondence.; Examinations (documents); Financial records.; Manuscripts for publication.; Notes (documents); Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Educators.; Theologians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Access to recordings requires advance notice to produce a use copy.
Acquisition Information
Gift of James Luther Adams.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Abingdon Press (Box 1)
  - Abraham, John (Box 1)
  - Abstracts, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Academy of Religion and Mental Health (Box 1)
  - Acquaviva (Box 1)
  - Action for a Federated World (Box 2)
  - Adams, Albert (Box 2)
  - Adams, Carol (Box 2)
  - Adams, Charles J. (Box 2)
  - Adams, Robert (Box 2)
  - Adams, Sherman (Box 2)
  - Adamson, Douglas (Box 2)
  - Administrative Policy, Committee on (Box 2)
  - Advisees (Box 2)
  - Ahlers, Rolf (Box 2)
  - Ahiheim, Klaus (Box 2)
  - Akashi, Michio (Box 2)
  - Akeley, T. Barton (Box 2)
  - Akita, Minoru (Box 2)
  - Akita, M. (prof. ) (Box 2)
  - All Souls Church, Unitarian, Washington, D.C. (Box 2)
  - Allen, Christine C., 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Allen, Harland (Box 2)
  - Allen, Henry, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Allen, Joseph J. (Box 2)
  - Allin, J. Bryan (Box 2)
  - Allport, Gordon (Box 2)
  - Allmog, J.R. (Box 2)
  - Altman, A. (Box 2)
  - Amelung, Eberhard, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Amelung, Walthar and Else (Box 3)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - American Academy of Religion (Box 4)
  - American Association for the United Nations, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - American Association of Theological Schools (Box 4)
  - American Association of University Professors (Box 4)
  - American Baptist Convention (Box 4)
  - American Catholic Sociological Society (Box 4)
  - American Christian Palestine Committee, 5 folders (Box 4, 5)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 6 folders (Box 5, 6)
  - American College in Jerusalem (Box 6)
  - American Committee for Christian German Refugees (Box 6)
  - American Committee for Cultural Freedom (Box 6)
  - American Committee on Africa (Box 6)
  - American Council of Learned Societies (Box 6)
  - American Council on Germany (Box 6)
  - American Friends Service Committee (Box 6)
  - American Histadrut/Cultural Exchange Institute (Box 6)
  - American Jewish Committee (Box 6)
  - American Journal of Sociology (Box 6)
  - American Medical Association (Box 6)
  - American Society for Political and Legal Philosophy, 2 folders (Box 6, 7)
  - American Society for the Study of Religion, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - American Society of Christian Ethics, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - American Society of Social Ethics, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - American Sociological Association (Box 7)
  - American Sociological Review (Box 7)
  - American Sociological Society (Box 8)
  - American Unitarian Association, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - American Unitarian Youth (Box 8)
  - American University (Box 8)
  - American Women in Radio and T.V. (Box 8)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 5 folders (Box 8, 9)
  - Americans United for Separation of Church and State, 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Ames,Van Meter (Box 9)
  - Ames, William E. (Box 9)
  - Amstutz, Jakob, 3 folders (Box 9, 10)
  - Anastos, M.V. (Box 10)
  - Anderson, Alan (Box 10)
  - Anderson, O.W. (Box 10)
  - Andover, Harvard (Box 10)
  - Andover, Newton, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Andreassion, Ben jouhie (Box 10)
  - Annin, William Stuart (Box 10)
  - Anshen, Ruth Nanda (Box 10)
  - Antioch (Box 10)
  - Arakawa, Diane (Box 10)
  - Aranguren (Box 10)
  - Arey, Lisa Trent (Box 10)
  - Arisian, Khoren, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Arkansas University (Box 10)
  - Armstrong, Gregory T. (Box 10)
  - Armstrong, S.A. (Box 10)
  - Arnold, John C. (Box 11)
  - Arnold, Mel (Box 11)
  - Arthur, Donald E. (Box 11)
  - Artificial Heart (Box 11)
  - Artificial Intelligence (Box 11)
  - Asakawa, H. (Box 11)
  - Aseltine, Herschel E. (Box 11)
  - Ashworth, Robert, Dr. (Box 11)
  - Asiedu, Leaps Y. (Box 11)
  - Asia, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Askew, R. (Box 11)
  - Association of Seminary Professors in the Practical Fields (Box 11)
  - Atherton Press, Inc. (Box 11)
  - Atomic Bomb, 2 folders (Box 11, 12)
  - Aubrey, Edwin F. (Box 12)
  - Ayer, Eric A. (Box 12)
  - Ayers, Francis (Box 12)
  - A-Ay, 5 folders (Box 12)
  - Babitt (Box 12)
  - Bach, Karl A. (Box 12)
  - Baehr, Karl, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Bailey, J.C. (Box 12)
  - Bailey, Mrs. Ralph E. (Box 12)
  - Baily, Nathan A. (Box 12)
  - Baldwin, Peter A. (Box 12)
  - Bales, R.F. (Box 13)
  - Ball, Milner (Box 13)
  - Bancroft, Nancy (Box 13)
  - Bangs, Carl and Jeremy (Box 13)
  - Barber, Benjamin (Box 13)
  - Barber, J. Stanley (Box 13)
  - Barnes, W. Graham, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Barnes, Grant (Box 13)
  - Barnett, Das Kelley (Box 13)
  - Barnette, Herlee H. (Box 13)
  - Barnum, Cyrus P. (Box 13)
  - Barrett, Evangeline (Box 13)
  - Barru, Paul S. (Box 13)
  - Bartchy, Scott S. (Box 13)
  - Barth, Carola, 2 folders (Box 13, 14)
  - Barth, Joseph, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Bassett, Joseph (Box 14)
  - Bartlett, Josiah R. (Box 14)
  - Bastian, Dwight (Box 14)
  - Bauer, Dietrich (Box 14)
  - Baumann, Agnes (Box 14)
  - Beach, Kim (Box 14)
  - Beach, G.K. (Box 14)
  - Beach, Waldo (Box 14)
  - Beachly, Alvin J. (Box 14)
  - Beacon Press, 3 folders (Box 14, 15)
  - Beattie, Paul H. (Box 15)
  - Beaver, R. Pierce (Box 15)
  - Becker, Howard (Box 15)
  - Becker, William (Box 15)
  - Bell, C.G. (Box 15)
  - Bellah, Robert (Box 15)
  - Ben Dor, Immanuel (Box 15)
  - Benda, Clemens (Box 15)
  - Bendix, Remhard Prof., 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Bennett, John C. (Box 15)
  - Bennett, Thomas (Box 15)
  - Bentley, Robert A. (Box 15)
  - Benton, Chandler (Box 15)
  - Benz, Ernst (Box 15)
  - Berger, Linda-Ruth (Box 15)
  - Berger, Peter C. (Box 15)
  - Berkshire Music Center (Box 15)
  - Berle, Adolf Jr. (Box 15)
  - Berman, Harold J. (Box 15)
  - Berridge, William A. (Box 15)
  - Berthold, Fred Jr. (Box 15)
  - Beswick, Paul (Box 15)
  - Beth, Marianne (Box 15)
  - Birmingham Unitarian Church (Box 15)
  - Birnbaum, Norman (Box 15)
  - Birth Control (Box 16)
  - Bixler, [Julius] Seelye (Box 16)
  - Blackburn, Chris (Box 16)
  - Blackhurst, J.H. (Box 16)
  - Blake, Glenn P. (Box 16)
  - Blakemore (Box 16)
  - Blanchard, Douglas & Family (Box 16)
  - Blanshard, P. (Box 16)
  - Blankenburg, Walther von (Box 16)
  - Bledsoe, Thomas A., 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Bleeker, C.J. (Box 16)
  - Bletzer, R. (Box 16)
  - Bliss, Paul Franklin (Box 16)
  - Blizzard, Samuel W. (Box 16)
  - Bloom, Alfred (Box 16)
  - Bloom, Sol (Box 16)
  - Bloy, Myron (Box 16)
  - B'Nai B'Rith (Box 16)
  - Bobrowski, Gerhard (Box 16)
  - Boeke, Richard F. (Box 16)
  - Boeyink, David E. (Box 16)
  - Bogosian, Ezekiel (Box 16)
  - Boisen, Anton (Box 16)
  - Boldizar, I. (Box 16)
  - Boney, William (Box 16)
  - Bonkowsky, F.O. (Box 16)
  - Booth, John Nicholls (Box 16)
  - Borman, Bernhard (Box 16)
  - Borreson, B. James, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Boston Theological Institute of Religion and the Arts (Box 16)
  - Boston University (Box 17)
  - Boston Renewal (Box 17)
  - Boston Theological Institute (Box 17)
  - Bowman, Robert M., 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Boyd, David P. (Box 17)
  - Boyer, Merle William (Box 17)
  - Box, Howard (Box 17)
  - Bradley, Karl (Box 17)
  - Bradley, William (Box 17)
  - Bragg, Raymond B. (Box 17)
  - Braisted, Paul J. (Box 17)
  - Branson, Roy E. (Box 17)
  - Braver; Jerald (Box 17)
  - Bridges, Gene (Box 17)
  - Brigham, Rev. J.W. (Box 17)
  - Bro, Harmon H. (Box 17)
  - Brody, Carol (Box 17)
  - Broehl, Wayne G. Jr. (Box 17)
  - Bronsen, David (Box 17)
  - Bronstein, Herbert (Box 17)
  - Brooke, Edward W. (Box 17)
  - Brooks, Howard L., 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Broome, Edwin C. (Box 17)
  - Brothen, Richard D. (Box 17)
  - Brothers of the Way (Box 17)
  - Brown, David (Box 18)
  - Brown, Dwight (Box 18)
  - Brown, H.O.J. (Box 18)
  - Brown, Kenneth I. (Box 18)
  - Brown, Kenneth R. (Box 18)
  - Brown, (General) (Box 18)
  - Browne, Conrad (Box 18)
  - Bruderhof Community (Box 18)
  - Brundage, Percival F., 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Buckley, Mary (Box 18)
  - Buehrer, Edwin T. (Box 18)
  - Bundy, McGeorge (Box 18)
  - Burgess, Laura M. (Box 18)
  - Burhoe, R.W. (Box 18)
  - Burkholder, J. Lawrence (Box 18)
  - Burleigh, Arthur C. (Box 18)
  - Burns, James H. (Box 18)
  - Burstatte, Elaine (Box 18)
  - Burton, Philip (Box 18)
  - Bush, Wallace (Box 18)
  - Bush, W.W. (Box 19)
  - Ba-By, 8 folders (Box 19)
  - Cacciola, Michelena (Box 19)
  - Cahill, Edward A. (Box 19)
  - Cairns, Huntington (Box 19)
  - California Press (Box 19)
  - Call, LonRay (Box 19)
  - Calvez, J--y (Box 19)
  - Cambridge (City) (Box 19)
  - Cambridge Civic Association (Box 19)
  - Cambridge University Press (Box 19)
  - Cameron, Angus deMille (Box 19)
  - Cameron, Ian (Box 19)
  - Campagnolo Umberto, 7 folders (Box 19, 20)
  - Campbell, Jeff (Box 20)
  - Campbell, John (Box 20)
  - Campbell, Levin H. (Box 20)
  - Campus Free College (Box 20)
  - Capiz, Ellen and Pascval (Box 20)
  - Carey, John J. (Box 20)
  - Carlson, Eric, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Carlson, Leyland H. (Box 21)
  - Carman, John B. (Box 21)
  - Carman, L.M. (Box 21)
  - Carnahan, Paul L. Jr. (Box 21)
  - Carnes, Paul (Box 21)
  - Carney, Frederick, 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Carpenter, Victor, 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Carrier, G. (Box 22)
  - Carrillo de Albornot, A.F. (Dr.) (Box 22)
  - Carter, H. Stewart (Box 22)
  - Carty, James W. Jr., 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Casparis, Hans, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Cassara, Ernest and Beverly (Box 22)
  - Cavanaugh, James H. (Box 22)
  - Caws, Peter (Box 22)
  - Cellar, Emanuel (Box 22)
  - Center for Population Studies (Box 22)
  - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions (Box 22)
  - Chandran, J. Russell, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Chang, Donald Mark (Box 22)
  - Chapmen, Paul H. (Box 22)
  - Chapman, Paul K. (Box 22)
  - Chandran, R. (Box 23)
  - Charlesworth, Max (Box 23)
  - Chase, Gilman (Box 23)
  - Cheng, Jill Tsui (Box 23)
  - Chesnut, Robert A. (Box 23)
  - Chicago, University of (Box 23)
  - Chicago, University of, Libraries (Box 23)
  - Chicago, University of, Press (Box 23)
  - Chicago Area Associate Alliance (Box 23)
  - Chicago Business Industries Project (Box 23)
  - Chicago Daily News (Box 23)
  - Chicago Memorial Association (Box 23)
  - Chicago President's School (Box 23)
  - Chicago Sun, Chicago Sun Times (Box 23)
  - Chicago Theological Seminar (Box 23)
  - Child Study Association of America (Box 23)
  - Chrisman, Miriam (Box 23)
  - Christian Action, 3 folders (Box 23)
  - Christian Century (Box 23)
  - Christian Register (Box 23)
  - Christian Research Foundation, 4 folders (Box 23, 24)
  - Christian Science Monitor (Box 24)
  - Christianity and Crises (Box 24)
  - Chung, Chai Sik (Box 24)
  - Church, F. Forrester (Box 24)
  - Church Peace Union (Box 24)
  - Ciba Foundation (Box 24)
  - Civil Liberties Union of Massachusetts (Box 24)
  - Claburn, William Eugene (Box 24)
  - Clark, Henry (Box 24)
  - Clark, Henry W. (Box 24)
  - Clark, John Rushkin, Jr. (Box 24)
  - Clark, John Ruskin (Box 24)
  - Clark, Thaddeus B. (Box 24)
  - Clark, Walter Houston (Box 24)
  - Clarke, David E. (Box 24)
  - Clarke, Ward R. (Box 24)
  - Clarke-McElroy Publishing Company (Box 24)
  - Clayton, John Powell (Box 25)
  - Clive, Geoffrey, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Cobb, John B., Jr. (Box 25)
  - Coburn, John G. (Box 25)
  - Coffin, Frank M. (Box 25)
  - Coffee, John M. (Box 25)
  - Cogley, John (Box 25)
  - Cohen, Arthur A. (Box 25)
  - Cohen, Robert S. (Dr.) (Box 25)
  - College Centers Comm. (Box 25)
  - Collier, Abram T. (Box 25)
  - Collmer, P. (Box 25)
  - Collmer, Willy (Box 25)
  - Colloquim (Box 25)
  - Comment, (A.D.Hellman, ed.) (Box 25)
  - Commission on Education (Box 25)
  - Committee for Academic and Professional Freedom (Box 25)
  - Committee for American College in Jerusalem (Box 25)
  - Committee for Disaster Relief in Cuba (Box 25)
  - Committee for the Journal (Box 25)
  - Committee on appointment (Box 25)
  - Committee on Educational Policy, 2 folders (Box 25, 26)
  - Commission on Planning and Review Politics (Box 26)
  - Committee to Aid Bloomington Students (Box 26)
  - Committee to Repeal (Box 26)
  - Committee to Salvage Talent (Box 26)
  - Community of Taize (Box 26)
  - Comprendre (Box 26)
  - Conference Board (Box 26)
  - Convocation (Box 26)
  - Conger, G.P. (Box 26)
  - Cooke, Gerald (Box 26)
  - Coolidge, Albert Sprague (Box 26)
  - Coon, Buelah I. (Box 26)
  - Cooper, Clara Chassell (Box 26)
  - Cooper, Harriet H. (Box 26)
  - Cooper, H. (Box 26)
  - Coordinating Council on the Free Church (Box 26)
  - Corbett, D., 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Corbett, Dorothy (Box 27)
  - Corwin, Virginia (Box 27)
  - Cosby, N.G. (Box 27)
  - Cotton, J. Harry, 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Council on Religion and International Affairs (Box 27)
  - Counselbaum, A.B.Stella (Box 27)
  - Cox, Harvey, 3 folders (Box 27)
  - Crain, Dale (Box 27)
  - Cramton, Roger and Harriet (Box 27)
  - Crary, Stephen T. (Box 27)
  - Crawford, C. (Box 27)
  - Cressy, Earl H. (Box 27)
  - Cronin, Leslie Westbrook (Box 27)
  - Crook, Margaret B., 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Crook, Wilfrid H. (Box 27)
  - Croos, Frank M. (Box 27)
  - Crout, William R. (Box 28)
  - Crowe, Michael Bertram (Box 28)
  - Crum, W.F. (Box 28)
  - Csiki, Gabriel Bishop (Box 28)
  - Cudhea, David (Box 28)
  - Cupples, John E. (Box 28)
  - Currier, Alvin C., 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Curti, Merle (Box 28)
  - Curtis, Jim (Box 28)
  - Cutler, Allan (Box 28)
  - Cyrus, John (Box 28)
  - Czaja, Herbert (Box 28)
  - Ca-Cu, 8 folders (Box 28)
  - Dadrain, Vahakn (Box 28)
  - Dalbeck, Gordon and Ruth (Box 28)
  - Daly, John Lawrence (Box 28)
  - Daly, Mary (Box 29)
  - Daly, Robert W. (Box 29)
  - Dana, Ellis H., 4 folders (Box 29)
  - Dana, Henry W.L. (Box 30)
  - Danforth Foundation, 2 folders (Box 30)
  - Daniel, Franz (Box 30)
  - Danielson, A. (Box 30)
  - Darling, Edward, 4 folders (Box 30)
  - Darling, Priscilla H. (Box 30)
  - Das, Basil P. (Box 30)
  - Daskam, Max (Box 30)
  - Daubney, R.H. (Box 30)
  - Daugherty, D.H. (Box 31)
  - Davis, Bertram H. (Box 31)
  - Davis, Forest R. (Box 31)
  - Davis, Harold M. (Box 31)
  - Day, Robert B. (Box 31)
  - Deale, Alan G. (Box 31)
  - Dean, Eric (Box 31)
  - Deane, Julia C. (Box 31)
  - Deats, Paul (Box 31)
  - DeBenneville (Box 31)
  - DeBoer, Hans A. (Box 31)
  - Deems Mervin (Box 31)
  - Deer, Lewis (Box 31)
  - DeLattre, R. (Box 31)
  - Demson, David (Box 31)
  - Denison University (Box 31)
  - Denman, Alvin (Box 31)
  - Denton, Charles (Box 31)
  - Derfer, G.E. (Box 31)
  - Desonay, Ferdinand (Box 31)
  - Despland, M. (Box 31)
  - Despres, Leon M. (Box 31)
  - Desroche, H., 2 folders (Box 31)
  - Deutsch, Alex T. (Box 31)
  - Deutsch, Siegfried (Box 31)
  - Dexter, Lewis A. (Box 31)
  - Dickinson College (Box 31)
  - Dillenberger, John (Box 31)
  - Dinkler, E. (Box 31)
  - Dirks, J. Edward (Box 31)
  - Dittes, J. (Box 31)
  - Dixon, John (Box 32)
  - Dodds, Robert C. (Box 32)
  - Dohrman, H. Theodore (Box 32)
  - Doi, Masatoshi, 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Dole, Kenneth (Box 32)
  - Dooley, Arch R. (Box 32)
  - Dorchester House Inc. (Box 32)
  - D'Orlando, Albert (Box 32)
  - Dougherty, Edward A. (Box 32)
  - Douglas, H. Paul (Box 32)
  - Dow Chemical Company (Box 32)
  - Dowling, Arthur P. (Box 32)
  - Downing, A. Ben (Box 32)
  - Drbolav, Karel (Box 32)
  - Drinan, Father Robert F. (Box 32)
  - Ducey, Michael H. (Box 32)
  - Duchay, Francis H. (Box 32)
  - Duchay, Francis H. (Box 32)
  - Duff, Edward (Box 33)
  - Dumpys, Hans G. (Box 33)
  - Dunbar, S. (Box 33)
  - Dunbar, William Scott (Box 33)
  - Dunham, M. (Box 33)
  - Dunn, Edmond J. (Box 33)
  - Duthie, C.S. (Box 33)
  - Dyck, Arthur (Box 33)
  - Da-Dy, 6 folders (Box 33)
  - East House, 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Eastman, Eleanor (Box 33)
  - Easton, Loyd D. (Box 33)
  - Eby, Kermit (Box 34)
  - Ecumenical Institute (Box 34)
  - Eddis, Charles W. (Box 34)
  - Ede, J. Chuter (Box 34)
  - Edmunds, D.W. (Box 34)
  - Edson, Cynthia (Box 34)
  - Educational Exchange (Box 34)
  - Edwards, David C. (Box 34)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight (Box 34)
  - Eisenstadt, V.S. (Box 34)
  - Eister, A.W. (Box 34)
  - Eliot, Frederick M. (Box 34)
  - Eller, Verhard (Box 34)
  - Elliot, John W. (Box 34)
  - Elliot, Katherine (Box 34)
  - Emanuel. Ben-Zion (Box 34)
  - Engagements, 2 folders (Box 34)
  - Engel, J. Ronald (Box 35)
  - Enquist, Roy (Box 35)
  - Ente, Dora (Box 35)
  - Epps, Archie (Box 35)
  - Erickson, Lowell L. (Box 35)
  - Ethics (Box 35)
  - Ethics Field (Box 35)
  - Eusden, John D. (Box 35)
  - Evans, Mack (Box 35)
  - Everett, William W., 3 folders (Box 35)
  - Eversole (Box 35)
  - Exams (Box 35)
  - Exman, Eugene (Box 35)
  - Exoo, George (Box 35)
  - El or Ell (Box 36)
  - Ev (Box 36)
  - E (misc. except El, Ell, Ev) (Box 36)
  - Faber, Dr. H. (Box 36)
  - Fackre, Gabriel (Box 36)
  - Fahs, Charles H. (Box 36)
  - Fahs, Sophia Lyon (Box 36)
  - Fairey, H.W. (Box 36)
  - Farris, Theodore N. (Box 36)
  - al Faruqi, Ismail R. (Box 36)
  - Faulhaber, R. (Box 36)
  - Fay, Leon C. (Box 36)
  - Feagin, Joe R. (Box 36)
  - Fehl, Noah E., 2 folders (Box 36)
  - Fellowship for Racial and Economic Equality (FREE) (Box 37)
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation (Box 37)
  - Fenn, Dan H. (Box 37)